Clarence Brown Papers, 1907-2005: Test EAD
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Princeton, N.J: Princeton University Press
Clarence Brown Papers
1907-2005
1907 2005
C1571
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
2 linear feet
3 boxes 12x40 Regular Hollingers
2 boxes 12x23.5 wonky size boxes
Brown Clarence
Consists of correspondence, travel diaries, photographs, and coursework of former Princeton University comparative literature professor Clarence Brown (1929-2015) relating primarily to his scholarship on Russian writers Osip Emilyevich Mandelstam (1891-1938) and Nadezhda Mandelstam (1899-1980). Correspondence with writer and illustrator Guy Davenport as well as with poet W. S. Merwin, Princeton Class of 1948, is also included.
Works Cited
Mandelʹshtam, Osip, and Clarence Brown.. The Prose of Osip Mandelstam: The Noise of Time, Theodosia, the Egyptian Stamp..
A scholar of modern Russian literature and translation, Clarence Brown (1929-2015) was a professor of comparative literature at Princeton University. He started at Princeton as an instructor in 1959 and became a professor in 1969, retiring in 1999. Brown first taught courses on Russian language and literature in the Department of Romance Languages and then in the Program in Slavic Languages and Literatures, which became a formal department in 1967. In 1971, he joined the Department of Comparative Literature.
Brown was most known for his scholarship on the Russian poet Osip Mandelstam (1891-1938), which was facilitated by the relationship he formed with Mandelstam’s widow and fellow writer, Nadezhda Mandelstam (1899-1980), who was invested in preserving her husband's work. The Prose of Osip Mandelstam (1965) was nominated for a National Book Award. Brown’s 1973 book Mandelstam earned him the Christian Gauss Award in Literary Criticism. Mandelstam’s papers, entrusted by Nadezhda to Brown in 1976, were donated to the Princeton University Library.
Brown earned his bachelor’s degree in classics at Duke University in 1950. After graduation, he was drafted and served four years in the Army Security Agency, including a year of intensive training in Russian at the Army Language School in Monterey, California, after which he was sent to Berlin as a German translator. He earned a master’s degree in linguistics in 1955 from the University of Michigan-Ann Arbor and his Ph.D. in Russian Literature from Harvard University in 1962.
A lifelong cartoonist, Brown’s work appeared in several publications, including Saturday Review, where he was cartoon editor from 1977 to 1984.
This collection consists primarily of correspondence along with some travel diaries, photographs, and coursework of comparative literature professor Clarence Brown (1929-2015). Much of the content, with the exception of correspondence with Guy Davenport, relates to the principal subject of Brown's scholarship, Russian poet Osip Emilyevich Mandelstam (1891-1938), as well as Mandelstam's wife, Nadezhda Mandelstam (1899-1980). This includes documentation about Brown's collaborative publication, Osip Mandelstam: Selected Poems (1974); Nadezhda Mandelstam's memoir Hope Against Hope (1970); and Osip Mandelstam's personal papers, which Nadezhda donated to Princeton University Library in 1976; among other topics. Correspondents who are well represented include writer and illustrator, Guy Davenport (1927-2005); poet W. S. Merwin (1927-), Princeton Class of 1948, with whom Brown collaborated on Osip Mandelstam: Selected Poems; and Nadezhda Mandelstam.
Open for research. Student coursework is restricted until 2044 or 75 years from the date of creation (1969) (housed in box B-001080).
Gift of Jacqueline Brown, 2017. (AM 2018-3)
No materials were separated during 2017 processing.
Osip Mandelstam Papers (C0539)
Akhmatova, Anna Andreevna, 1889-1966; Mandelʹshtam, Nadezhda, 1899-1980; Mandelʹshtam, Osip, 1891-1938; Davenport, Guy; Merwin, W.S. (William Stanley), 1927-; Princeton University. Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures; Literature and state -- Soviet Union -- 20th century -- Sources.; Princeton University -- Faculty -- 20th century -- Sources.; Russian poetry -- 20th century -- Sources.; Russian prose literature -- 20th century -- Sources.; Translators in literature -- Sources.; Russian literature -- Translations into English -- Sources.; Soviet Union -- Intellectual life -- 1917-1970 -- Sources.; Soviet Union--Description and travel.; Correspondence -- 20th century.; Manuscripts.; Poets, Russian -- 20th century.; Cold War; Literature; Princeton University; Russia
- Correspondence, 1945-2005; 3 boxes One partial.
  Most of the correspondence is with Brown's close friend, Guy Davenport. Correspondence with W. S. Merwin is primarily about their collaborative translation work: Osip Mandelstam: Selected Poems (1974) and includes translations of Osip Mandelstam's poetry. Letters with Nadezhda Mandelstam relate to her memoir, Hope Against Hope.
  Other correspondents include former Princeton professor of Slavic languages and literatures, Charles Townsend, Boris Filippov, and Vladimir Nabokov, among others.
  The organization of the correspondence that existed at the time of acquisition was maintained.
  - Guy Davenport, 1945 2005; 2 boxes One partial.
    Includes mostly incoming letters, though some are from Brown, of a largely personal nature. Many letters are addressed to Clarence and Jacqueline Brown or to the entire family, particularly those dating from the 1960s. Letters include discussion of each others' literary interests, publications, projects, the work of other academics, and their respective teaching positions, among other topics.
    Also included is a folder of poems by Davenport dedicated to Brown.
    - Guy Davenport, 1945-1950; 1 folder (Folder 1)
      Includes some discussion of Davenport's studies at Duke and Oxford.
    - Guy Davenport, 1949-1959; 1 folder (Folder 2)
      Includes Davenport's letter of recommendation for Brown for the Rhodes Scholarship (1949) as well as correspondence from when Davenport was stationed at Fort Bragg, North Carolina. Some letters discuss of Davenport's studies at Harvard and work at Washington University.
    - Guy Davenport, 1959-1969; 1 folder (Folder 3)
    - Guy Davenport, 1966-1979; 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Guy Davenport, 1980-1989; 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Guy Davenport, 1990-1994; 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Guy Davenport, 1995-1999; 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Le sens du monde, 1993; 2.4.5.34 (M); 1 folder (Folder 8)
      Paris: Galilée
      Passages with heavy annotations present.
      Inscribed copy.
      Includes manuscript material.
      Dealer note: Dédicace: "pour Jacques et pour Marguerite, affectueusement J-Luc" Trouvé sur le rayon entre les docs 2.4.5.34 (M) et 2.4.35 (M): Billet de Rodolphe Burger, accompagnant une version tapuscrite de "La voix de Jean-Luc" qu'il a fait parvenir à JD. Texte et billet déposés ensemble avec la correspondance le 13-04-201.
      Check-in observation: Bookmarks on pages 100-101, 102-103, 114-115, 118-119, 142-143, 150-151, 154-155, 168-169, 222-223. Dog-eared pages 178, 225, 237.
      Finalism (Philosophy); Teleology; Annotations (Provenance); Inscriptions (Provenance); Insertions (Provenance)
    - Le sens du monde Jean-Luc Nancy Finalism (Philosophy) Teleology, 2.4.5.34 (M); 1 thing (Folder 8)
      Annotations (Provenance); Inscriptions (Provenance); Insertions (Provenance)
- 32101080849969 (Box B-001076)